[Music]
in a video i did a few years ago i
talked about how press releases about
the latest science coming out of even
top medical centers were filled with
overstatements and omissions
medical journal press releases suffered
from similar problems and press releases
from the drug companies themselves were
no different filled with hype and
exaggeration
what about press releases issued by the
supplements industry
not even the companies that published
the studies but like trade organizations
for the multi-billion dollar dietary
supplement industry researchers found
that a hundred percent of supplements
industry press releases contained spin
meaning strategies to hype or denigrate
findings to distort the results of
clinical studies
and here's the crazy part industry press
releases advocated supplement use in
response to more than 90 percent of even
the studies that reported no benefit or
harm
here are the harm studies
a study comes out showing a supplement
is actually bad for you and the vast
majority of independent institutions
like the national institutes of health
or mainstream media stories are like
don't take it
duh
but the industry trade organizations are
like harm
go for it buy an extra bottle it is
therefore likely that the propagation of
the spin enriched industry press
releases contributes to the ongoing and
even burgeoning enthusiasm for use of
supplements in the face of accumulating
evidence of most of their
ineffectiveness and in some cases harm
in some cases people are paying to make
themselves sick
sadly the science may not even matter to
many supplement users most dietary
supplement users said that they would be
minimally influenced by independent
taxpayer-funded studies contradicting
the efficacy claims of supplement
manufacturers only a minority of users
said that they would stop taking a
supplement if public health authorities
stated that it was just a waste of money
the iconic image of the snake oil
salesman was actually
a real dude clark the rattlesnake king
stanley in 1916.
turns out that stanley's snake oil in
fact contained no snake oil at all but
rather just like
spicy mothballs and turpentine
prosecuted under the newly enacted pure
food and drug act and ultimately fined a
lofty sum of
20 bucks
and a century later here we are with
snakewell coming out our years a vast
number of supplements marketed and sold
without routine oversight
now the supplement industry bristles at
such talks saying that the supplement
industry is regulated to protect
consumers and it's true there are
definitely laws on the books but the
ability of regulators to successfully
carry out this mission is hampered by
the sheer number of products the fda
estimates there are more than 85 000
dietary supplement products currently
available in the us alone so there's the
sheer number the under reporting of
adverse side effects the difficulty of
successfully prosecuting cases against
offenders and the ease with which
suppliers can rebrand products removed
from the shelves have led to a largely
unregulated environment in the real
world there's little guarantee that a
supplement will even contain what is
advertised on the packaging and not
contain unlisted ingredients potentially
leading to significant harms resulting
in an estimated 23 000 er visits every
year
now of course prescription drugs don't
just sicken but kill many more making
them perhaps the third leading cause of
death wiping out more than a hundred
thousand americans
but still the less death and disability
the better
dietary supplements are often
adulterated with undeclared
pharmaceuticals which could represent an
enormous risk to consumers most often
found in erectile dysfunction weight
loss diabetes and high blood pressure
supplements
but wait a second
what about supplement manufacturers who
say they have independent third party
certification of purity
there's a practice called dry labbing a
dirty little secret of the supplements
industry where quality assurance labs
just rubber stamp fake documents and if
you think that's outrageous check out
the story of bmpea
a researcher at harvard published a
paper replicating prior research from
the fda detecting a designer
amphetamine-like stimulant
beta-methylphenylethylamine in various
us supplements sold in the united states
in response one of the offenders
high-tech pharmaceuticals manufacturers
of weight loss supplements like black
widow and yellow scorpion
sued the harvard researcher for libel
slander and product disparagement
originally to the tune of 200 million
dollars in damages
this was all documented in a piece by
stat
which is an excellent source of medical
journalism that i recommend
the head of high tech openly admitted
that he was hoping that we were able to
silence this guy and while ultimately
unsuccessful in court high-tech's
lawsuit effectively sent a warning to
other researchers
in fact high-tech ceo is attributed to
saying he hopes that the long and costly
legal battle will scare away other
academics from investigating the
supplement industry
[Music]
you